Guide to the North America Taiwanese Women's Association Records
University of Houston Libraries
North America Taiwanese Women's Association Records
1989-2013
02/2013-006
North America Taiwanese Women's Association
6.50 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection includes the photographs, publications, and ephemera belonging to the North America Taiwanese Women’s Association. Materials are arranged topically and then chronologically, whenever possible. The series included are: Photo Albums/Scrapbooks, Publications, and Ephemera. The bulk of the materials are written primarily in Taiwanese except for the cookbooks which also include the English translation of the text.
Historical Note:
Founded on 13 March 1988, the North America Taiwanese Women’s Association (NATWA) organized during an era when Taiwanese women had no independent organization to represent them. In 1987, Ms. Maysing Yang became the Taiwanese American Association’s (TAA) first female president and ushered in a new era for Taiwanese women. Enlisting the services of Ms. Annette Lu, founder of Taiwan’s women’s movement, to aid in planning, the first steps toward a women’s branch of the TAA began to take shape. In March of 1988, thirty Taiwanese women from the United States and Canada met in Los Angeles and under the guidance of Ms. Lu, voted to form NATWA.
The members voted Fu-Mei-Chang of San Jose first President, with Grace Chou serving as Vice-President and president elect. At the same time, seven by-law board members were also elected and in July of the same year 45 members voted to approve the official by-laws. The seven board members, having concluded their duties, became the first seven regional board members representing US East, US Midwest, US West, US South, US Great Plains, US Southeast, and Canada. The organization continued to grow for the following six years when the sixth president, Ying Lee, broadened NATWA’s structure. During her tenure, Ms. Lee organized committees and create formal job descriptions for office holders.
NATWA continues to grow to this day with the participation of over 1,000 members. Run primarily by volunteers, the organization boasts a healthy financial standing due to its publications, especially its yearly calendar. Though faced with obstacles on the world stage, NATWA has garnered more support in the foreign community and in December 2000, NATWA became one of the five collaborating members of the World Taiwanese Congress.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Calendars; Ephemera; Periodicals; Publications (document genre)
Topical Term:
Asian American women; North America Taiwanese Women's Association; Women -- Societies and clubs
Acquisition Information:
Donated by North American Taiwanese Women's Association, 2013
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes the photographs, publications, and ephemera belonging to the North America Taiwanese Women’s Association. Materials are arranged topically and then chronologically, whenever possible. The series included are: Photo Albums/Scrapbooks, Publications, and Ephemera. The bulk of the materials are written primarily in Taiwanese except for the cookbooks which also include the English translation of the text.
Detailed List of Contents
- Photo Albums/Scrapbooks
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains photo albums and scrapbooks maintained by NATWA. All materials for the corresponding year were contained in individual albums or binders. The binders and albums have been deconstructed and preserved in archival sleeves though the original order has been maintained. Two oversized albums remain intact and can be located in OVS Box 5. Any written material and photograph captions within this series are written primarily in Taiwanese.
  - 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 2005 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1993-1994 (Ovsbox 5, Item 1)
  - 1993-1994 (Ovsbox 5, Item 2)
- Printed Materials
  This series consists of printed materials published by NATWA. Included are the complete collections of membership directories, convention handbooks, magazines and calendars. The calendars are an important part of the NATWA tradition. First thought of by Ms. Annette Lu as a means to promote Taiwan, the calendars began with a donation by Japanese businessman Ing-Ke Kao and the annual publication has been instrumental in the organization’s financial success. All publications held in this series are primarily written in Taiwanese.
  - Membership Directory
    - 1990-1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 2010-2012 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Convention Handbooks
    - 1995-1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 2000-2003 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 2004-2008 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 2009-2013 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - NATWA Magazine
    - 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 2006-2007 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 2008-2009 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 2010-2011 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 2012-2013 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Calendars
    - Calendars (13), 1991-2013 (Ovsbox 4, Item 1)
  - Various
    - Resource Handbook, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Q & A Series, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Caring Book Series, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Our Stories, by Carol Yang, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Homestyle Cooking of Taiwan, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Taiwanese Homestyle Cooking, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Ephemera
  This series contains materials related to NATWA but does not fit into any previous series. Included are banners, scarves and a pin all decorated with the NATWA logo.
  - Canvas Bag, undated (Ovsbox 4, Item 2)
  - Large Banner, 2003 (Ovsbox 4, Item 3)
  - Small Banner, 2003 (Ovsbox 4, Item 4)
  - Scarf, 2003 (Ovsbox 4, Item 5)
  - Scarf, 2012 (Ovsbox 4, Item 6)
  - Pin, undated (Ovsbox 4, Item 7)